<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://alejandralopezgalan.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://alejandralopezgalan.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2025-07-31T01:43:57+00:00</updated><id>https://alejandralopezgalan.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>PhD in Neuroscience. Data Analyst. SQL, Excel &amp; data visualisation tools. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">Holidays in Germany</title><link href="https://alejandralopezgalan.github.io/blog/2025/blog2/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Holidays in Germany"/><published>2025-03-06T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-03-06T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://alejandralopezgalan.github.io/blog/2025/blog2</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://alejandralopezgalan.github.io/blog/2025/blog2/"><![CDATA[<p>It’s March 2025, and I’ve been wanting to write a blog about my past winter holidays in Germany, but work as a teacher hasn’t left me much spare time to continue with my blog. Nevertheless, I’ve finally organised my day to write, and here I am.</p> <p>In December 2024, I had the incredible opportunity to visit Germany for the first time. The holiday season made it even more special, with festive markets and rich cultural experiences. I landed at Munich International Airport, where my friend picked me up, and we took the train to Deggendorf, where we stayed for the two weeks I had for my holidays. She had already been living there for a couple of months, and thankfully she knew how to get around the area and helped me get everything I needed for the holidays.</p> <p>One of the most memorable parts of my trip was visiting the famous Christmas markets. It was my first time experiencing them, and honestly, words cannot describe how much I loved them. The first Christmas market I went to was in Deggendorf, it was small but beautiful. I indulged in Baumstriezel filled with chocolate and topped with sweet cinnamon, and mulled wine (Glühwein). After that day, I had Glühwein at every Christmas market I visited.</p> <div class="row justify-content-sm-center"> <div class="col-sm-4 mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/blog2-deggendorf-market-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/blog2-deggendorf-market-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/blog2-deggendorf-market-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/blog2-deggendorf-market.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <div class="col-sm-6 mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/blog2-deggendorf-market-view-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/blog2-deggendorf-market-view-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/blog2-deggendorf-market-view-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/blog2-deggendorf-market-view.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> Enjoying Baumstriezel and Glühwein at Deggendorf Christmas market. </div> <p>We travelled by train every time we went out, and I thoroughly enjoyed the view during the journey. It was relaxing, and although my knowledge of the German language was almost zero, my partner did a superb job of getting us wherever we needed to be. However, I didn’t like that the trains were not always on time—aren’t Germans known for their punctuality?</p> <p>Passau was the second city we visited, and at the Christmas market, there was a kissing station. To keep up with the tradition, my partner and I kissed under the mistletoe</p> <div class="row justify-content-sm-center"> <div class="col-sm-4 mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/blog2-passau-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/blog2-passau-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/blog2-passau-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/blog2-passau.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <div class="col-sm-4 mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/blog2-passau-market-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/blog2-passau-market-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/blog2-passau-market-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/blog2-passau-market.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> Drinking Glühwein at Passau Christmas market. </div> <p>The third place we visited was Regensburg. We took a bus to visit the Walhalla temple, which resembles the Parthenon in Athens. The temple and the view were majestic, as was St. Peter’s Cathedral with its Gothic architectural style.</p> <div class="row"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/blog2-walhalla1-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/blog2-walhalla1-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/blog2-walhalla1-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/blog2-walhalla1.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/blog2-walhalla-view-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/blog2-walhalla-view-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/blog2-walhalla-view-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/blog2-walhalla-view.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/blog2-st-peter-cathedral-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/blog2-st-peter-cathedral-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/blog2-st-peter-cathedral-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/blog2-st-peter-cathedral.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> Walhalla temple, the view from the temple, and St. Peter's Cathedral in Regensburg. </div> <p>The next city we visited was Salzburg. We had the chance to visit the Hohensalzburg Fortress, one of the largest and oldest museums for art and cultural history in Salzburg. It is a must-visit place if you enjoy learning about history, medieval collections, and war.</p> <div class="row"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/blog2-museum-salzburg-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/blog2-museum-salzburg-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/blog2-museum-salzburg-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/blog2-museum-salzburg.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/blog2-castle-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/blog2-castle-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/blog2-castle-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/blog2-castle.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/blog2-salzburg-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/blog2-salzburg-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/blog2-salzburg-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/blog2-salzburg.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> Exhibition view "Weapons in the Middle Ages" at the Fortress Museum, a photo from Hohensalzburg Fortress, and the Salzach river in Salzburg. </div> <p>Our next day trip was to Dachau, where the first and longest-operating Nazi concentration camp was built. We visited the Concentration Camp Memorial, and it was a unique experience. In this museum, we learned about Nazi propaganda, entered the bunkers used for torture, the crematorium, the gas chamber, and through photos, we learned about the atrocities and the horrible conditions the prisoners endured. In my opinion, it is an experience that everyone should have to learn not only about history and war, but to understand what humans are capable of doing to our own species. I don’t know if it was because the weather was really cold that day, but I felt an eerie energy the whole time I was in the museum.</p> <div class="row"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/blog2-dachau3-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/blog2-dachau3-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/blog2-dachau3-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/blog2-dachau3.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/blog2-dachau2-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/blog2-dachau2-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/blog2-dachau2-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/blog2-dachau2.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/blog2-dachau-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/blog2-dachau-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/blog2-dachau-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/blog2-dachau.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> Camp road and the reconstructed barracks, bunkers used to keep special prisoners, ovens inside the crematorium at the Dachau concentration camp. </div> <p>We continued our trip in Nuremberg, another city well-known for its history, as the Nuremberg Trials were held there. After the war, Allied powers—the United States, Great Britain, France, and the Soviet Union—came together to form the International Military Tribunal (IMT), and the Nazi German leaders stood trial for crimes against peace, war crimes, crimes against humanity, and conspiracy to commit any of the foregoing crimes. We decided to take this trip to enjoy the view of the city and took a tourist train to get to know this beautiful city better. One thing I remember from this place is that it is also famous for its Nuremberg sausages, or Nürnberger Rostbratwurst, which are German pork sausages known for their small size and smoky flavour. I am a vegetarian though, so I did not try them.</p> <div class="row"> <div class="col-sm-3 mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/blog2-nuremberg-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/blog2-nuremberg-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/blog2-nuremberg-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/blog2-nuremberg.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <div class="col-sm-4 mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/blog2-nuremberg2-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/blog2-nuremberg2-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/blog2-nuremberg2-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/blog2-nuremberg2.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <div class="col-sm-4 mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/blog2-nuremberg3-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/blog2-nuremberg3-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/blog2-nuremberg3-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/blog2-nuremberg3.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> View of the Pegnitz River, St. Sebaldus Church, and Glühwein at Nuremberg. </div> <p>Sadly, our vacation came to an end, and the last city we visited was Munich. I couldn’t leave without having more Glühwein and a pretzel to finish this wonderful and memorable trip around Bavarian cities. I hope I can visit Germany again and enjoy everything it has to offer tourists like myself. I would definitely go again at Christmas, as it is my favourite time of the year, and they truly embrace the Christmas spirit. Tschüss Deutschland.</p> <div class="row"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/blog2-munich-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/blog2-munich-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/blog2-munich-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/blog2-munich.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/blog2-munichgluwein-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/blog2-munichgluwein-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/blog2-munichgluwein-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/blog2-munichgluwein.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/blog2-pretzel-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/blog2-pretzel-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/blog2-pretzel-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/blog2-pretzel.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> Munich at night, more Glühwein, and me enjoying a Pretzel from the Rischart Cafe on Marienplatz. </div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="life-experiences"/><category term="Holidays"/><category term="Germany"/><category term="Europe"/><category term="Christmas"/><category term="Travel"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[December holidays and festive experiences]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">A teacher’s Journey to Data Analyst</title><link href="https://alejandralopezgalan.github.io/blog/2024/blog1/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A teacher’s Journey to Data Analyst"/><published>2024-12-19T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-12-19T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://alejandralopezgalan.github.io/blog/2024/blog1</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://alejandralopezgalan.github.io/blog/2024/blog1/"><![CDATA[<p>Hello, my name is Alejandra, but people call me Alex or Ale (pronounced “ah-leh” in Spanish).</p> <p>In this post, I’ll share a bit about myself and my journey to becoming a Data Analyst.</p> <p>I have a background in Marine Biology, and it was during the last year of my bachelor’s studies that my interest in Data Analysis was sparked. We learnt about statistics and how to analyse biological data. As I conducted research for my honours thesis, I started developing my skills in R programming.</p> <p>I followed the research path and decided to pursue a PhD in visual ecology at the University of Queensland in Australia, where I further honed my data analysis, statistics, data visualisation, and R programming skills.</p> <p>I loved doing marine biology research in Australia; it was truly a privilege. I explored wonderful places during my studies and met amazing people. However, sometimes unexpected things happen, such as the COVID-19 pandemic, and the plans you had can change without warning.</p> <p>I moved back to my home country, Mexico, and started over. I knew that as much as I loved doing research, it was not something I wanted to do for the rest of my career. Nonetheless, I needed a job, and I was lucky enough to find one within three months, starting as a teacher in a private high school.</p> <p>I began teaching Geography, then Ecology, and finally the elective Critical Thinking. I didn’t plan on teaching for long—maybe just one or two years—but once again, things didn’t go as expected, and here I am, four years into teaching.</p> <p>This job is demanding, but honestly, I got through a very difficult time thanks to my students. They might not know it, but showing up, talking to them, teaching them, and learning from them really helped me when I was going through an emotional rollercoaster. I should also thank my amazing therapist, who helped me when I felt lost. What I can tell you from this experience is to be kind to everyone; you don’t know what they are going through. Even when they seem happy, they might be fighting some emotional battles.</p> <p>Let’s go back to the main topic: why become a Data Analyst? Well, why not? As I mentioned before, I was fascinated by statistics since I was an undergrad. It was something that I was good at and quick to learn. I would say that if you study something related to natural science, you need to learn statistics. We use it to prove that the data from our experiments are reliable and might or might not be significant. Thanks to my formal education, I can confidently say that I am competent in data visualisation, spreadsheets, statistics, analysing data, R programming, data cleaning, and data collection.</p> <p>I could also say that my experience in teaching and supervising students, both at secondary and tertiary education levels, has helped me to develop some of the non-technical skills you need to be a good data analyst: problem-solving, communicating to diverse audiences, writing, attention to detail, and critical thinking.</p> <p>As I started to take my goal of becoming a Data Analyst more seriously, I decided to purchase a <a href="https://www.datacamp.com/">DataCamp</a> membership to learn some of the skills I needed, such as SQL and Data Visualisation in PowerBI and Tableau, and to brush up on my Spreadsheet skills. I know that there are free resources that you can find on YouTube and other places, but for me, it is best to find the information I need in one place, at least to know where to start.</p> <p>Then I started to listen to some podcasts on Spotify that talked about transitioning to a Data Analyst role, such as the <a href="https://datacareerpodcast.com/">Data Career Podcast</a> with Avery Smith, <a href="https://carrerascientificasalternativas.com/podcast-entrevistas/">Carreras Científicas Alternativas</a> (in Spanish) with Manolo Castellano, <a href="https://www.superdatascience.com/podcast">Super Data Science: ML &amp; AI Podcast with Jon Krohn</a> with Jon Krohn, and <a href="https://mavenanalytics.io/mavens-of-data">Mavens of Data</a> with the team from Maven Analytics. The more I got into it, the more I learnt that in order to land a job, I needed to work on my portfolio, build projects, and network. So here I am, it is almost the end of the year and I want to step up my game, and that is why I decided to work on my webpage, my portfolio, and be more active on LinkedIn.</p> <p>Thanks for reading this blog, and if you want to connect with me, you can find me on <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/alejandralopezgalan/">LinkedIn</a> or any of my socials.</p> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/blog1-workbiology-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/blog1-workbiology-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/blog1-workbiology-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/blog1-workbiology.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <p>Drying wetsuits after diving was part of the work as a marine biologist.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/blog1-workbiology2-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/blog1-workbiology2-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/blog1-workbiology2-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/blog1-workbiology2.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <p>Flying over the Great Barrier Reef is one of my favorite memories.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/blog1-workbiology3.JPG-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/blog1-workbiology3.JPG-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/blog1-workbiology3.JPG-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/blog1-workbiology3.JPG" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <p>I’m very grateful for making friendships that last even after the PhD.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="career-transition"/><category term="data"/><category term="analytics"/><category term="teacher"/><category term="career"/><category term="change"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[How it all started]]></summary></entry></feed>