<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://alejandralopezgalan.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://alejandralopezgalan.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2024-12-07T22:46:19+00:00</updated><id>https://alejandralopezgalan.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>PhD in Neuroscience. Data Analyst. SQL, Excel &amp; data visualisation tools. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">A teacher’s Journey to Data Analyst</title><link href="https://alejandralopezgalan.github.io/blog/2024/blog1/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A teacher’s Journey to Data Analyst"/><published>2024-12-07T15:40:16+00:00</published><updated>2024-12-07T15:40:16+00:00</updated><id>https://alejandralopezgalan.github.io/blog/2024/blog1</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://alejandralopezgalan.github.io/blog/2024/blog1/"><![CDATA[<p>Hello, my name is Alejandra, but people call me Alex or Ale, which is pronunce “ah-leh” in Spanish. In this post I will take about myself and my journey to become a Data Analyst. I have a background in Marine Biology, and it was during the last year of my bachelor studies where my interest in Data Analysis sparked. We learnt about statistics and how to analyse biological data. As I conducted research for my honours thesis I started developing my skill in R programming.</p> <p>I followed the research path, and decided to pursue a PhD in visual ecology at the University of Queensland, in Australia, where I grow my data analysis, statistics, data visualisation, and R programming skills even further.</p> <p>I loved doing marine biology research in Australia, it was truly a privilege. I explored wunderfull places during my studies and met amazing people; however, sometimes unexpected things happen, such as the COVID-pandemic, and the plans you had can change witouth anticipation.</p> <p>I moved back to my home country, Mexico, and I started all over. I knew that as much as I loved doing research, it was not something I wanted to do for the rest of my career. Nonetheless, I needed a job, and I was lucky enough to take only three months to start as a teacher in a private high school.</p> <p><a href="https://www.pinterest.com">Pinterest</a> DIY authentic Schlitz, hoodie Intelligentsia butcher trust fund brunch shabby chic Kickstarter forage flexitarian. Direct trade <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cold-pressed_juice">cold-pressed</a> meggings stumptown plaid, pop-up taxidermy. Hoodie XOXO fingerstache scenester Echo Park. Plaid ugh Wes Anderson, freegan pug selvage fanny pack leggings pickled food truck DIY irony Banksy.</p> <h4 id="hipster-list">Hipster list</h4> <ul> <li>brunch</li> <li>fixie</li> <li>raybans</li> <li>messenger bag</li> </ul> <h4 id="check-list">Check List</h4> <ul class="task-list"> <li class="task-list-item"><input type="checkbox" class="task-list-item-checkbox" disabled="disabled" checked="checked"/>Brush Teeth</li> <li class="task-list-item"><input type="checkbox" class="task-list-item-checkbox" disabled="disabled"/>Put on socks <ul class="task-list"> <li class="task-list-item"><input type="checkbox" class="task-list-item-checkbox" disabled="disabled" checked="checked"/>Put on left sock</li> <li class="task-list-item"><input type="checkbox" class="task-list-item-checkbox" disabled="disabled"/>Put on right sock</li> </ul> </li> <li class="task-list-item"><input type="checkbox" class="task-list-item-checkbox" disabled="disabled" checked="checked"/>Go to school</li> </ul> <p>Hoodie Thundercats retro, tote bag 8-bit Godard craft beer gastropub. Truffaut Tumblr taxidermy, raw denim Kickstarter sartorial dreamcatcher. Quinoa chambray slow-carb salvia readymade, bicycle rights 90’s yr typewriter selfies letterpress cardigan vegan.</p> <hr/> <p>Pug heirloom High Life vinyl swag, single-origin coffee four dollar toast taxidermy reprehenderit fap distillery master cleanse locavore. Est anim sapiente leggings Brooklyn ea. Thundercats locavore excepteur veniam eiusmod. Raw denim Truffaut Schlitz, migas sapiente Portland VHS twee Bushwick Marfa typewriter retro id keytar.</p> <blockquote> <p>We do not grow absolutely, chronologically. We grow sometimes in one dimension, and not in another, unevenly. We grow partially. We are relative. We are mature in one realm, childish in another. —Anais Nin</p> </blockquote> <p>Fap aliqua qui, scenester pug Echo Park polaroid irony shabby chic ex cardigan church-key Odd Future accusamus. Blog stumptown sartorial squid, gastropub duis aesthetic Truffaut vero. Pinterest tilde twee, odio mumblecore jean shorts lumbersexual.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="career-transition"/><category term="data"/><category term="analytics"/><category term="teacher"/><category term="career"/><category term="change"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[How it all started]]></summary></entry></feed>